<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<manpage program="ovsdb" section="5" title="OVSDB">
  <h1>Name</h1>
  <p>ovsdb -- Open vSwitch Database (File Formats)</p>

  <h1>Description</h1>
  <p>
    OVSDB, the Open vSwitch Database, is a database system whose network
    protocol is specified by RFC 7047.  The RFC does not specify an on-disk
    storage format.  The OVSDB implementation in Open vSwitch implements two
    storage formats: one for standalone (and active-backup) databases, and the
    other for clustered databases.  This manpage documents both of these
    formats.
  </p>

  <p>
    Most users do not need to be concerned with this specification.  Instead,
    to manipulate OVSDB files, refer to <code>ovsdb-tool</code>(1).  For an
    introduction to OVSDB as a whole, read <code>ovsdb</code>(7).
  </p>

  <p>
    OVSDB files explicitly record changes that are implied by the database
    schema.  For example, the OVSDB ``garbage collection'' feature means that
    when a client removes the last reference to a garbage-collected row, the
    database server automatically removes that row.  The database file
    explicitly records the deletion of the garbage-collected row, so that the
    reader does not need to infer it.
  </p>

  <p>
    OVSDB files do not include the values of ephemeral columns.
  </p>

  <h2>Common Features</h2>

  <p>
    Standalone and clustered database files share the common structure
    described here.  They are text files encoded in UTF-8 with LF (U+000A) line
    ends, organized as append-only series of records.  Each record consists of
    2 lines of text.
  </p>

  <p>
    The first line in each record has the format <code>OVSDB <var>magic</var>
    <var>length</var> <var>hash</var></code>, where <var>magic</var> is
    <code>JSON</code> for standalone databases or <code>CLUSTER</code> for
    clustered databases, <var>length</var> is a positive decimal integer, and
    <var>hash</var> is a SHA-1 checksum expressed as 40 hexadecimal digits.
    Words in the first line must be separated by exactly one space.
  </p>

  <p>
    The second line must be exactly <var>length</var> bytes long (including the
    LF) and its SHA-1 checksum (including the LF) must match <var>hash</var>
    exactly.  The line's contents must be a valid JSON object as specified by
    RFC 4627.  Strings in the JSON object must be valid UTF-8.  To ensure that
    the second line is exactly one line of text, the OVSDB implementation
    expresses any LF characters within a JSON string as <code>\n</code>.  For
    the same reason, and to save space, the OVSDB implementation does not
    ``pretty print'' the JSON object with spaces and LFs.  (The OVSDB
    implementation tolerates LFs when reading an OVSDB database file, as long
    as <var>length</var> and <var>hash</var> are correct.)
  </p>

  <h2>Standalone Format</h2>

  <p>
    The first record in a standalone database contains the JSON schema for the
    database, as specified in RFC 7047.
  </p>

  <p>
    The second and subsequent records in a standalone database are transaction
    records.  Each record may have the following optional special members,
    which do not have any semantics but are often useful to administrators
    looking through a database log with <code>ovsdb-tool show-log</code>:
  </p>

  <dl>
    <dt><code>_date</code></dt>
    <dd>
      <p>
        The time at which the transaction was committed, as an integer number
        of milliseconds since the Unix epoch.  Early versions of OVSDB counted
        seconds instead of milliseconds; these can be detected by noticing that
        their values are less than 2**32.
      </p>

      <p>
        OVSDB always writes a <code>_date</code> member.
      </p>
    </dd>

    <dt><code>_comment</code></dt>
    <dd>
      <p>
        A JSON string that specifies the comment provided in a transaction
        <code>comment</code> operation.  If a transaction has multiple
        <code>comment</code> operations, OVSDB concatenates them into a single
        <code>_comment</code> member, separated by a new-line.
      </p>

      <p>
        OVSDB only writes a <code>_comment</code> member if it would be
        nonempty.
      </p>
    </dd>
  </dl>

  <p>
    Each record has one or more additional members, each of which maps from the
    name of a database table to a &lt;table-txn&gt; that describes the effects
    of a transaction on the named database table.  A &lt;table-txn&gt; is a
    JSON object whose names are 36-character strings representing a UUID in the
    format described by RFC 4122.  Each member of a &lt;table-txn&gt; describes
    the effects of the transaction on the row whose UUID is named.  A
    <code>null</code> value indicates that the transaction deleted the row.
    Otherwise, the value is a &lt;row-txn&gt; object that describes how the
    transaction inserted or modified the row.  Each member of a &lt;row-txn&gt;
    object maps from the name of a column to the column's new value as a
    &lt;value&gt; defined in RFC 7047.  For new rows, the OVSDB implementation
    omits columns whose values have the default values for their types defined
    in RFC 7047 section 5.2.1; for modified rows, the OVSDB implementation
    omits columns whose values are unchanged.
  </p>

</manpage>
